<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>World of Dualities</title>
    <description>Random ramblings of a software geek.
</description>
    <link>http://krishna.nadiminti.me/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://krishna.nadiminti.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2015 03:09:01 +1000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2015 03:09:01 +1000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.0.pre.beta8</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Yet Another Getting Started Post - Blog with Octopress 3 on Windows 10</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TLDR;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blog more than you tweet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Static blogs are great if you are a developer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Octopress is a good platform to setup a technical blog, but you need to know Jekyll first&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setting it up on Windows is slightly tricky if you are new to Ruby&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This post has some useful tips to help you with that&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-blog&quot;&gt;Why blog?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was recently evaluating the kind of activities I was doing on a daily basis and found that I was consuming a lot more content that creating it. Also, I was spending &lt;a href=&quot;http://keysleft.com/&quot;&gt;a lot more keystrokes&lt;/a&gt; on twitter than a less ephemeral medium like a blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, inspired by Scott Hanselman’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hanselman.com/blog/YourWordsAreWasted.aspx&quot;&gt;urging devs to blog more&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to do some more blogging. (Let’s see how this turns out!)
I had a very minor presence before on &lt;a href=&quot;http://krishnanadiminti.blogspot.com.au/&quot;&gt;blogger&lt;/a&gt; - but wanted to own my content from now on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, I spent some (too much?) time trying to decide a good platform to setup my blog - and thought it might be a good idea to post my thoughts and struggles when I finally managed to get this blog up and running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://staticsitegenerators.net/&quot;&gt;statically generated site&lt;/a&gt;, without the &lt;a href=&quot;https://google.com/search?q=wordpress%20vs%20jekyll&quot;&gt;headaches of performance and security&lt;/a&gt; are very appealing to me.
Looking at what others have done, I found that &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; is a popular platform, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/octopress/octopress&quot;&gt;Octopress&lt;/a&gt; seemed to improve upon it.
So after considering various options, I settled on using Octopress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where ‘the fun’ began.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;my-starting-point&quot;&gt;My starting point&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a web developer who’s spent a lot of time on the Microsoft stack. Windows is my main OS - and I’d never developed with the Ruby language/ecosystem. I plan to go into more detail in a separate post about the specific technical issues I had to solve, but this post about is what worked for me in the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main issue I found with various (helpful) blog posts around the web describing how to use Octopress / Jekyll was a ton of unsaid assumptions - and a primary focus on devs who already knew Ruby or were on a Mac/Linux etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to avoid that, so here goes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;assumptions&quot;&gt;Assumptions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You are a web developer on Windows looking to setup a ‘statically generated’ blog&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You know about DNS in general and can figure out how to setup domains etc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can deal with the commandline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You know about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.git-scm.com/&quot;&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt; (an awesome distrbuted version control system) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and already have git installed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You know about &lt;a href=&quot;http://chocolatey.org&quot;&gt;Chocolatey&lt;/a&gt; (a great machine package manager for Windows)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You know about &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/articles/markdown-basics/&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You’re willing to try out new things&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You don’t know much about Ruby (in reality, this post has nothing much to do with Ruby anyway - other than setting it up so Octopress can be installed and used)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-i-will-cover&quot;&gt;What I will cover&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Basic setup of Octopress on Windows (what worked for me)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some thoughts on how I setup my repo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-i-will-not-cover--repeat&quot;&gt;What I will not cover / repeat&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blogging with Octopress/Jekyll in detail (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=getting+started+with+octopress&quot;&gt;there is a lot of information about that out there&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setting up DNS and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;Github pages&lt;/a&gt; (which is a free service to host your websites)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setting up search, comments and bunch of other things that are really needed if you want a more full-featured blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-octopress-3-on-windows-10-and-publish-to-github-pages&quot;&gt;Using Octopress 3 on Windows 10 and publish to Github pages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of this, my plan was to:
- Have a Github pages hosted statically generated blog (for free)
- Have my custom domain pointed to it
- (Later) Be able to easily add some of the features/services found on a more full-featured platform like &lt;a href=&quot;http://wordpress.com&quot;&gt;Wordpress&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;setup-steps&quot;&gt;Setup steps:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Install Ruby using Chocolatey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an &lt;em&gt;admin PowerShell session&lt;/em&gt;, run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  choco install ruby -y
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chocolatey installs applications at &lt;code&gt;C:\tools&lt;/code&gt; by default. I personally don’t like that - but I can live with it: they have their reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gave me Ruby at &lt;code&gt;C:\tools\ruby21&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Install DevKit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ruby has a package manager (gem - like Nuget in the Microsoft world) - and some packages need native ‘compilation’ after installation. This is what the DevKit enables/simplifies? on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;!--Installing DevKit via Chocolatey is far from perfect. I found this out the hard way.--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same admin PowerShell session, run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  choco install ruby2.devkit -y
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gave me Ruby DevKit at &lt;code&gt;C:\tools\DevKit2&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, the DevKit installation (tried and) did not discover where Ruby was installed. So I had to tell it where to find Ruby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the &lt;code&gt;C:\tools\DevKit2\config.yml&lt;/code&gt; file and add the following line at the end (this is the location of your Ruby installation) (&lt;em&gt;note the forward slashes&lt;/em&gt; and include the &lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt; at the beginning):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  - C:/tools/ruby21
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Install Octopress (which brings Jekyll with it)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you can use the gem package manager to install the Octopress gem (i.e package).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  gem install octopress
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Setup a new blog using Octopress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The docs on Github for Octopress assumes a lot and (to me) wasn’t clear if you started with a &lt;code&gt;init&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;new&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that if you have nothing are you want to start a new Octopress blog, you can run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  octopress new blog
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will create a directory called &lt;code&gt;blog&lt;/code&gt;, setup Jekyll (as if  you ran &lt;code&gt;jekyll new&lt;/code&gt;), and initialise Octopress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Setup a Git repo for the Octopress blog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left the Git setup till after I got Octopress setup locally - because this was something I already knew how to do, but I was (still am) not sure what the best way to setup the Octopress blog repo is for my needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t want people to view my half-baked draft posts. So for now, I decided to setup another ‘remote’ for my git repo - on &lt;a href=&quot;http://bitbucket.org&quot;&gt;Bitbucket&lt;/a&gt;, which is another good place to host your source repositories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I set it up with:&lt;br /&gt;
   - A remote on Bitbucket to hold the blog source, settings etc.
   - A remote on Github to publish the generated site to Github pages using Octopress&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting up Octopress deployment to Github involves running:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  octopress deploy init git https://github.com/krishna-nadiminti/krishna-nadiminti.github.io.git
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;from your blog directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When trying to deploy to Github, at one point Octopress complained - and gave me some guidance on how to setup the repo. This happened when I was on the &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; branch with some uncommitted changes. Octopress said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  You cannot deploy to the same branch you are working in.
  This will overwrite the source for your site.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I’m not sure if this is the right way to set it up, but I have it working this way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  git remote -v

  deploy  https://github.com/krishna-nadiminti/krishna-nadiminti.github.io.git (fetch)
  deploy  https://github.com/krishna-nadiminti/krishna-nadiminti.github.io.git (push)
  origin  https://bitbucket.org/krishna_nadiminti/blog.git (fetch)
  origin  https://bitbucket.org/krishna_nadiminti/blog.git (push)

  git branch

  master
  * source
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, a remote called &lt;code&gt;deploy&lt;/code&gt; pointing to Github which seems to be the default remote Octopress uses to publish changes, and &lt;code&gt;origin&lt;/code&gt; is the source on Bitbucket, and a branch called &lt;code&gt;source&lt;/code&gt; to keep the source files, and &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; for deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case I have the following in my &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  _site
  .sass-cache
  .jekyll-metadata
  _deploy.yml
  .deploy
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that Octopress is setup, let’s briefly look at the directory structure it created (note that I didn’t yet setup themes and other integrations):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog-dir.png&quot; alt=&quot;Blog directory structure&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;publish-flow&quot;&gt;Publish flow&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flow I’m using to get my blog posts published is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create/Edit a (new) page / post / draft using :
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Octopress commands (octopress new draft / post / page)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Or using your favorite editor, create .md files in &lt;code&gt;_drafts&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;_pages&lt;/code&gt; folders&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add your post content using the markdown syntax to your &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; file&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generate your blog using &lt;code&gt;jekyll build&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you created a draft, you need to &lt;code&gt;octopress publish _drafts/[file name of draft.md]&lt;/code&gt; before you build it, to see it on the generated site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Save and preview by running &lt;code&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt; (and browsing to &lt;code&gt;http://localhost:4000&lt;/code&gt; - the default server jekyll runs up for previewing your blog)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once you are happy, commit your changes to Git and deploy using &lt;code&gt;octopress deploy&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Push to the remote where the source is (because Octopress just deploys the generated content under its &lt;code&gt;_sites&lt;/code&gt; folder)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enjoy, profit, get rich etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this post will help someone trying to setup Octopress on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till next time…take it easy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2015 22:26:12 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://krishna.nadiminti.me/2015/08/17/yet-another-getting-started-post-octopress-3-on-windows-10/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://krishna.nadiminti.me/2015/08/17/yet-another-getting-started-post-octopress-3-on-windows-10/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
